A Guide to the Accomack County (Va.) Deeds, 1701-1838 (bulk 1737-1820)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Accomack County (Va.) Deeds, 1701-1838 (bulk 1737-1820)
The Library of Virginia
1133721, 1133678, 1133728, 1133677, 1133719, 1133732, 1133725, 1133727, 1133718, 1133729, 1133731
6.75 cu. ft. (15 boxes)
Accomack County (Va.) Circuit Court
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These items came to the Library of Virginia in transfer of court papers from Accomack County.
Historical Information
Accomack County was named for the Accomac Indians, who lived on the eastern Shore at the time of the first English settlement in Virginia. One of the original eight shires established in 1634, Accomac County (spelled without a k) became Northampton County in 1643. The present county was formed from Northampton in 1663. In 1940 the General Assembly adopted the county's present spelling.
Scope and Content
Accomack County (Va.) Deeds, 1701-1838 (bulk 1737-1820) predominantly consist of deeds of bargain and sale, deeds of gift, mortgages, and deeds of trust. On presentation to the court, deeds were proved and recorded. If the deed was not witnessed, the grantor acknowledged the deed in open court. A few of the deeds include plats.
Deeds of bargain and sale are the most commonly recorded deed in which one individual sells property, usually land, but occasionally personal property, to another individual. Such deeds show the names of the grantor and grantee, the residence of both parties, a description of what is being sold, the consideration (or price), the location of the tract of land, the tract's boundaries, and any limitations on the property being sold. The deed was signed by the grantor, and possibly his wife or anyone else having a claim to the property, and by at least two witnesses. Appended to the deed may be a memorandum of livery of seisin, stating that the property has changed hands and that peaceful possession has taken place.
Deeds of gift are often found transferring property, either real or personal, from one individual to another "for love and affection." The degree of kinship, if any, between the grantor and grantee is sometimes stated.
Mortgages and deeds of trust were deeds where one party is indebted to another and transfers or mortgages property to a third party to secure the debt.
The collection also includes deeds of emancipation and manumission, bills of sale related to transactions of enslaved people, certificates of importation of enslaved people, and apprenticeship indentures involving free people of color.
Arrangement
Chronological
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Deed Books and Indices to Deeds for Accomack County can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia. Consult A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm
Additional Accomack County Land Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia web site. Consult A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm
Digital images for deeds of emancipation and manumission, bills of sale related to transactions of enslaved people, certificates of importation of enslaved people, and apprenticeship indentures involving free people of color are available on the Virginia Untold: the African American Narrative web site.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Accomack County (Va.) Circuit Court
Subjects:
African American--History; Land subdivision--Virginia-Accomack County; Slaveholders--Virginia--Accomack County; Slavery--Virginia--Accomack County; Slaves--Virginia--Accomack County
Geographical Names:
Accomack County (Va.)--History
Genre and Form Terms:
Deeds--Virginia--Accomack County; Land records--Virginia--Accomack County; Local government records--Virginia--Accomack County; Mortgage deeds--Virginia--Accomack County
Contents List
- Deeds 1701-1732; 1737-1784 (Barcode 1133721)
- Deeds 1785-1789 (Barcode 1133678)
- Deeds 1790-1793 (Barcode 1133728)
- Deeds 1794-1796 (Barcode 1133677)
- Deeds 1797-1799 (Barcode 1133719)
- Deeds 1799-1801 (Barcode 1133732)
- Deeds 1801-1804 (Barcode 1133725)
- Deeds 1804-1806 (Barcode 1133727)
- Deeds 1806-1808 (Barcode 1133718)
- Deeds 1808-1809 (Barcode 1133729)
- Deeds 1810-1813 (Barcode 1133731)
- Deeds 1813-1816 (Barcode 1133704)
- Deeds 1816-1817 (Barcode 1133702)
- Deeds 1817-1818 (Barcode 1133551)
- Deeds 1819-1820; 1827-1828; 1838 (Barcode 1133685)